Guide to the Helayne Spivak papers, 1972-2015 and undated RL.11757
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Helayne Spivak papers
1972-2015 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Spivak, Helayne
RL.11757
9.0 Linear Feet
Helayne Spivak is an advertising executive and educator based in New York and Richmond, Va. Collection includes awards, clippings, correspondence, print advertisements and other printed materials as well as audiovisual materials (audio tapes, videocassettes, 16mm films, optical disks, video reels). Companies and agencies represented include Ally & Gargano, Barneys department store, Cadbury, Club Med, Commodore computer, Dunkin' Donuts, Federal Express, J. Walter Thompson, Pan Am, Schweppes, and Travelers. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General Files; Print Advertisements; Audiovisual Materials.
Biographical / Historical
Helayne Spivak is an advertising executive and educator based in New York and Richmond, Va.
Born 1953, New York. Parsons School of Design. Ally & Gargano 1976-1986 (copywriter, Associate Creative Director); Ammirati & Puris 1986-1989 (Creative Director); Hal Riney 1989-1990 (Executive Vice President, Creative Director); Young & Rubicam 1990-1993 (Executive Vice President, Creative Director); Ammirati & Puris 1993-1996 (Chief Creative Officer, Worldwide Creative Director); J. Walter Thompson 1996-1997 (Worldwide Creative Director, Chief Creative Officer); Messner Vetere Berger MacNamee Schmetterer 1997-2000 (consultant); Tatham 2000 (Interim Creative Partner); Artustry Partnership 2000 (Creative Partner); Energy BBDO 2003 (Group Creative Director); CCA Advertising 2006 (Chief Creative Officer); Saatchi & Saatchi Wellness 2008-2011 (Chief Creative Officer); VCU Brandcenter 2012-2017 (Director).
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed until use copies can be produced.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Helayne Spivak papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2017-2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Amil Gargano papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Account files
J. Walter Thompson Company. Biographical files
J. Walter Thompson Company. Competitive advertisements
J. Walter Thompson Company. Corporation vertical files
J. Walter Thompson Company. Domestic advertisements
J. Walter Thompson Company. Iconographic materials
Joy Golden papers
Stuart Elliott papers
Wells Rich Greene Inc. records.
Collection Overview
Collection includes awards, clippings, correspondence, print advertisements and other printed materials as well as audiovisual materials (audio tapes, videocassettes, 16mm films, optical disks, video reels). Companies and agencies represented include Ally & Gargano, Barneys department store, Cadbury, Club Med, Commodore computer, Dunkin' Donuts, Federal Express, J. Walter Thompson, Pan Am, Schweppes, and Travelers. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Advertising; Advertising -- United States -- History; Department stores -- Advertising; Advertising agencies; Advertising executives; Women in the advertising industry; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Pan American World Airways, Inc.; Young & Rubicam; J. Walter Thompson Company; Travelers Insurance Companies; Cadbury Beverages, Inc.; Schweppes (Firm)
- General Files, 1972-2015 and undated; 1
  - Accounts--Aleve storyboard, undated (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Accounts--Bic merchandising book, undated (Box 1)
  - Accounts--Commodore Max Machine launch booklet, undated (Box 1)
  - Accounts--Dunkin' Donuts script, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Accounts--Travelers--Protection magazine, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Ally & Gargano floor plan, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Awards, 1988-1993 (Box 1)
  - Awards--Andy, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Awards--Clio, 1978-1983 (Box 6)
  - Awards--Matrix, 1992-1996 (Box 1)
  - Awards--Matrix, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Awards--One Show 77/78, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Awards--One Show, 1980-1990 (Box 5)
  - Awards--One Show, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Bill Bernbach's Book (Bob Levinson, signed by author), 1987/2012 (Box 4)
  - Cartoon--Why Do You Feel Discriminated Against, Miss Spivak? (Marisa Acocella), approximately 1999 (Box 4)
  - CCA Advertising--You Are Entering the State of Wellness, undated (Box 6)
  - Clippings (articles, press notices), 1976-2014; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Clippings (articles, press notices), 1987-1997 (Box 4)
  - Clippings (articles, press notices), 1988-1997 (Box 6)
  - Clippings (articles, press notices), 1979-2014 (Box 7)
  - Clippings (articles, press notices)--Crain's People to Watch, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence--Congratulations, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Joan Rivers, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Working Woman (includes article draft), 1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1988-2015 and undated (Box 1)
  - Diary (day books, planners), 1987-1997; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - JWT suit--Defendants' memorandum, 1998 (Box 2)
  - JWT suit--Press coverage, 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Miami Ad School thank you card, 1999 (Box 7)
  - Ogilvy on Advertising/Advertising on Ogilvy (book, video box set), undated (Box 4)
  - One (One Club publication), 1997 (Box 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 6)
  - Proclamation, Mayor of New York, Women's History Month, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Speech--Breaking Creative Barriers, undated (Box 2)
  - VCU Brandcenter candidate meeting book, 2012 (Box 2)
  - VCU Brandcenter schedules, 2014-2016 (Box 6)
  - Wall Street Journal, Creative Leaders Series, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Wall Street Journal, Creative Leaders Series posters, 1992-1995 (Box 8)
- Print Advertisements, 1976-1987 and undated; 2
  - Ally & Gargano laminate, 1985 (Box 8)
  - Barney's, 1977-1979 and undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Barney's, 1978 and undated (Box 7)
  - Barney's, 1977-1978; 2 folders (Box 8)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes public service ads: Voting, Fresh Air Fund
  - Barney's laminates, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
  - Beefeater Gin, undated (Box 3)
  - Beefeater Gin, undated (Box 7)
  - Club Med, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Club Med laminates, 1987 (Box 7)
  - CocoRibe, undated (Box 3)
  - CocoRibe, undated (Box 4)
  - CocoRibe, 1981 (Box 7)
  - Commodore, undated (Box 3)
  - Commodore Vic 20 laminates, 1982 (Box 8)
  - Dunkin' Donuts, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Federal Express laminates, 1982 (Box 8)
  - Fiat, undated (Box 3)
  - Fiat laminates, undated (Box 7)
  - In-Materials, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Interwoven Mills laminates, undated (Box 7)
  - Karastan, undated (Box 7)
  - Karastan laminates, 1982 and undated (Box 7)
  - New Yorker, undated (Box 6)
  - Pan American, 1976 and undated (Box 3)
  - Pan American, 1976-1978; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Pan American, 1976-1977 and undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Pan American, 1976 and undated (Box 8)
  - Pan American laminates, 1977 and undated (Box 7)
  - Philip Landek Productions laminate, undated (Box 7)
  - The Copy Club, undated (Box 3)
  - The Parent Helpline (City of New York Human Resources Administration), undated (Box 3)
  - The Parent Helpline laminates, undated (Box 7)
  - Soap laminates, undated (Box 7)
    Includes: Pierre Cardin Collection; Continental Collection (Ariano, Juilly, Sarria)
  - Travelers insurance, undated (Box 3)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1978-2004 and undated; 3
  - Ally & Gargano spots, undated (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL11757-RR-001)
    Includes: Polish Man (Pan Am); Michael (Pan Am); Shearling Outerwear (Barney's); Family Album (Pan Am); Cashmere in the Oak Room (Barney's); Go for Dough (Dunkin' Donuts); Fresh Air Fund (Barney's); Young and Hungry; Hungry Artist; I'm Wanda (Dunkin' Donuts)
  - Ally & Gargano spots, undated (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL11757-RR-002)
  - Dunkin' Donuts radio, 1978 (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL11757-RR-003)
    Includes: Young and Hungry; Hungry Artist
  - Helayne Spivak compilation, undated (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL11757-RR-004)
    Includes: Polish Man (Pan Am); Mother (MCI); Family Album (Pan Am); Hang Ups (MCI); Fresh Air Fund (Barney's); Young and Hungry (Dunkin' Donuts); Wats on First (MCI); Big Z (MCI)
  - Parent Helpline "Problems" :60, undated (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL11757-RR-005)
  - Schweppes spots, 1987 (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL11757-RR-006)
    Includes: Auction; Roderick; Fizz
  - Untitled compilation, undated (Box AV3, Film-reel RL11757-F16-001)
  - Untitled compilation, undated (Box AV3, Film-reel RL11757-F16-002)
  - Saatchi & Saatchi Consumer Healthcare; DTC Perspective Video (Napoleon Group), 2004 (Box AV1, Video-disc RL11757-OP-001)
  - AAAA annual meeting, "Selling with Attitude", 1992 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-001)
  - Advertising on Ogilvy (from box set), undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-002)
  - "All About Women" Helayne Spivak, Women in Advertising, CNN Network, 2:58, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-003)
  - "All About Women" Helayne Spivak, Women in Advertising, CNN Network, 2:58, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-004)
  - Ammirati Puris Lintas humor reel, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-005)
  - Berwyn various spots, 2000 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-006)
  - Bloomberg Forum, Helayne Spivak interview, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-007)
  - Helayne Spivak compilation, 2000 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-008)
  - Helayne Spivak compilation, 2000 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-009)
  - Helayne Spivak compilation--Artustry Partnership, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-010)
  - Helayne Spivak CNBC Power Lunch, 1997 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-011)
  - Helayne Spivak CNBC Power Lunch, 1997 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-012)
  - TV's Favorite Commercials (entire TBS program) 60:00, 1997 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-013)
  - Woman in Advertising, CNN Today, 3:10, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-VHS-014)
  - Ally & Gargano spots, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-Umatic-001)
    Includes: Hang Ups; Taste Test; Evolution; Reminder; Easy Dough; Reach Out; Party
  - Ammirati & Puris/Lintas reel, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-Umatic-002)
    Includes spots from Epson, Compaq, Burger King, Lego, Aetna, Johnson & Johnson, UPS, MasterCard, RCA
  - Ammirati & Puris/Lintas reel, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-Umatic-003)
    Includes spots from Compaq, Burger King, Lego, Aetna, Johnson & Johnson, UPS, MasterCard, RCA, Labatt
  - Bloomberg Forum, Helayne Spivak interview, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-Umatic-004)
  - Ammirati Puris Lintas compilation, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-Umatic-005)
    Includes spots from Epson, Compaq, Reckitt & Colman, Burger King, Sara Lee/Bali, Aetna, UPS, Johnson & Johnson, MasterCard, RCA
  - Helayne Spivak AAAA annual meeting "Selling with Attitude", 1992 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-Umatic-006)
  - Helayne Spivak, Young & rubicam New York reel, undated (Box AV3, Video-cassette RL11757-Umatic-007)
    Includes spots from Club Med, Acutrim, MCI, Schweppes, Keller Geister, Sanyo, RNC
  - Helayne Spivak JWT Worldwide Creative Director interview, 1996 (Box AV3, Video-cassette RL11757-Umatic-008)
  - Compilation, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-Bcam-001)
    Includes: Club Med "World News"; Night Time Refrigerator; Hang Ups; Sundae; Broom Closet; Dobbs; Somewhere; Frazzled; John Cleese; all spots from reel 7; transferred from 1"
  - Helayne Spivak compilation, 2000 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-Bcam-002)
    Includes: Club Med "World News"; Acutrim "Refrigerator"; Schweppes "Dobbs"; MCI "Hang Ups"; Club Med "Somewhere"; Acutrim "Sundae"; Burger King "Nothing Like"; Sanyo "Broom Closet"; Club Med "Frazzled"; Sears "Excitement Lift"; UPS "Early AM"; MCI "News bulletin"; Schweppes "John Cleese"
  - Helayne's reference reel, JWT Worldwide Executive Group Meeting, 1997 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11757-Bcam-003)
  - All spots, undated (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-001)
  - Ally & Gargano spots, 1986 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-002)
    Includes: Night Time Refrigerator; Advice; Party; Hang Ups; Wallet; Evolution; Reminder; Easy Dough; Customer Service; Sundae; Food Things; Vignettes; Reach Out; Broom Closet
  - Cadbury-Schweppes, Royal Seltzer and Ginger Ale 2 spots, 1988 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-003)
  - Chiquita "Dick Clark", "Rona Barrett" :30, 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-004)
  - Club Med 5 spots, 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-005)
    Includes: Romantic Girl; Eater; Kids; Girlfriends; Windsurfer
  - Club Med "Frazzled" :30, 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-006)
  - Club Med "Somewhere" :30, 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-007)
  - Club Med "World News" :30, 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-008)
  - National Distillers, Keller Geister Wine historical cassette, 1985 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-009)
  - NCL Cruises 2 spots, 1986 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-010)
    Includes: Man and Woman; Runaway Man
  - New York Post 3 spots, 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-011)
    Includes: Sundae; Doctor; Big Paper
  - Schweppes 4 spots, 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-012)
    Includes: Full Line "Line"; Raspberry Ginger Ale "Hall of Fame"; Ginger Ale "British-American"; "Very British-American"
  - Schweppes Corporate "Gratuitous Violence" 117 sec., 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-013)
  - Schweppes Corporate "John Cleese" :90 agency version, 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-014)
  - Schweppes "Dobbs" :30, 1987 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-015)
  - Schweppes Raspberry Ginger Ale "Duchess" and diet cans :30, 1989 (Box AV2, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-016)
  - Schweppes Tonic "Faint" 10 oz. bottle, agency mix :30, 1989 (Box AV3, Video-reel RL11757-Vid1-017)